<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ascii'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>


<rfc category="bcp"
  docName="draft-ietf-mtgvenue-iaoc-venue-selection-process-04"
  ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" updates="" xml:lang="en">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Venue Selection">IETF Plenary Meeting Venue Selection
      Process</title>

    <author fullname="Ray Pelletier" initials="R." surname="Pelletier">
      <organization>Internet Society</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street />
          <city />
          <code />
          <region />
          <country />
        </postal>
        <email>rpelletier@isoc.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Laura Nugent" initials="L." surname="Nugent">
      <organization>Association Management Solutions</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street />
          <city />
          <code />
          <region />
          <country />
        </postal>
        <email>lnugent@amsl.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dave Crocker" initials="D." role="editor"
      surname="Crocker">
      <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street />
          <city />
          <code />
          <region />
          <country />
        </postal>
        <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lou Berger" initials="L." surname="Berger">
      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street />
          <city />
          <code />
          <region />
          <country />
        </postal>
        <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ole Jacobsen" initials="O." surname="Jacobsen">
      <organization>The Internet Protocol Journal</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street />
          <city />
          <code />
          <region />
          <country />
        </postal>
        <email>olejacobsen@me.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jim Martin" initials="J." surname="Martin">
      <organization>INOC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street />
          <city />
          <code />
          <region />
          <country />
        </postal>
        <email>jim@inoc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Fred Baker" initials="F.J." role="editor" surname="Baker">
      <organization />
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street />
          <city>Santa Barbara</city>
          <code>93117</code>
          <region>California</region>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>FredBaker.IETF@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>mtgvenue</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The IAOC has responsibility for arranging IETF plenary meeting Venue
        selection and operation. This document details the IETF's Meeting Venue
        Selection Process from the perspective of its goals, criteria and
        thought processes. It points to additional process documents on the IAOC
        Web Site that go into further detail and are subject to change with
        experience.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>The IAOC has responsibility for arranging IETF plenary meeting venue
        selection and operation. This document describes the IETF Meeting Venue
        Selection Process from the perspective of goals, criteria and thought
        processes. It describes the objectives and principles behind the Venue
        selection process. It also discusses the actual selection process to one
        level of detail, and points to working documents used in execution. </t>

      <section title="Background">
        <t>Following IETF 94 and at IETF 95 there was a discussion on the IETF
          list of the selection process and criteria for IETF meetings. In
          response to that discussion, the IAOC and the IAOC Meetings Committee
          took it upon themselves to more publicly document its process and
          refine it, based on community input.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="*** Post-Seoul Revisions ***">
        <t>Comments on this post-Seoul version:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Many items from the Sullivan draft have been included.</t>
            <t>A number of criteria had confusing wording and have been revised.
              The confusion was about the difference between a process that must
              be followed, versus a decision based on that process. Following
              the process is Mandatory. The details of the decision, however,
              are not pre-determined.</t>
            <t>Extensive reformulation of the document layout.</t>
          </list>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="EDITOR'S DISCLAIMER:  ">This attempts to reflect the
              work of the Seould mtgvenue discussions but is certain to have
              missed and/or misinterpreted quite a bit. Some changes were the
              result of off-list discussions; they seem to resolve specific
              issues but of course the final decision rests with the working
              group... Please post explicit text change requests to the list.
              /Dave</t>
        </list></t>
        <section title="*** Approach to the -04 ***">
          <t>This document started with draft-ietf-mtgvenue-iaoc-venue-selection-process-03 as the base and attempts to incorporate the ideas from <xref target="I-D.sullivan-mtgvenue-decisions" />. Requirements have been added from that draft to this one and grouped together in <xref target="criteria" /> with the existing requirements from draft-ietf-mtgvenue-iaoc-venue-selection-process-03.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

<!--      <section anchor="reqslang" title="Requirements Language">
        <t>Requirements called out in this document are identified by the degree
          of requirement. The labels that are used are: <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Mandatory:  "><vspace />If this requirement cannot be
              met, a location under consideration is unacceptable. We walk
              away.</t>
            <t hangText="Important:  "><vspace />Does not qualify as Mandatory,
              but is still highly significant; can possibly be traded off
              against other Important considerations.</t>
            <t hangText="Desired:  "><vspace />We would very much like to meet
              this requirement, but the failure to meet it will not disqualify a
              Venue.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
-->
</section>

    <section anchor="objectives" title="Venue Selection Objectives">

      <section anchor="core" title="Core Values">

        <t>The IETF has some core values that pervade the selection process. The
          values are not limited to the following, but at minimum include them.
            <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Why do we meet?"><vspace />We meet to pursue the IETF's
              mission <xref target="RFC3935" />, partly by advancing the
              development of Internet-Drafts and RFCs. We also seek to
              facilitate attendee participation in multiple topics and to enable
              cross-pollination of ideas and technologies.</t>

            <t hangText="Inclusiveness:"><vspace />We would like to facilitate
              the onsite or remote participation of anyone who wants to be
              involved.</t>
            <t>Every country has limits on who it will permit within its
              borders. However the IETF seeks to: <list style="numbers">
                <t>Minimize situations in which onerous entry regulations
                  prevent participants from attending meetings, or failing that
                  to distribute meeting locations such that onerous entry
                  regulations are not always experienced by the same attendees;
                  and</t>
                <t>Avoid meeting in countries with laws that effectively exclude
                  people on the basis of race, religion, gender, sexual
                  orientation, national origin, or gender identity.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="Where do we meet?"><vspace />We meet in different
              locations globally, in order to spread the difficulty and cost of
              travel among active participants, balancing travel time and
              expense across the regions in which IETF participants are
              based.</t>

            <t hangText="Internet Access:"><vspace />As an organization, we
              write specifications for the Internet, and we use it heavily.
              Meeting attendees need unfiltered access to the general Internet
              and our corporate networks, which are usually reached using
              encrypted VPNs from the meeting Venue and hotels, including
              overflow hotels. We also need open network access available at
              high enough data rates, at the meeting Facility, to support our
              work, including the support of remote participation. <xref
                target="MeetingNet" /></t>

            <t hangText="Focus:"><vspace />We meet to have focused technical
              discussions. These are not limited to scheduled breakout sessions,
              although of course those are important. They also happen over
              meals or drinks -- including a specific type of non-session that
              we call a "Bar BOF" -- or in side meetings. Environments that are
              noisy or distracting prevent that or reduce its effectiveness, and
              are therefore less desirable as a meeting Venue.</t>

            <t hangText="Economics:"><vspace />Meeting attendees participate as
              individuals. While many are underwritten by employers or sponsors,
              many are self-funded. In order to reduce participation costs and
              travel effort, we therefore seek locations that provide convenient
              budget alternatives for food and lodging, and which minimize
              travel segments from major airports to the Venue. Within reason,
              budget should not be a barrier to accommodation.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="nonobjectives" title="Venue Selection Non-Objectives">
        <t>IETF meeting Venues are not selected or declined with the explicit
          purposes of:<list style="hanging">

            <t hangText="Politics:  "><vspace />Endorsing or condemning
              particular countries, political paradigms, laws, regulations, or
              policies.</t>

            <t hangText="Maximal attendance:  "><vspace />Because the IETF
              garners a significant portion of its revenue from IETF meeting
              fees, there is considerable incentive for decision- makers to
              prefer a Venue that will attract more attendees. It is important
              to resist this temptation: a larger meeting in which key
              contributors could not make it is not a better meeting; neither is
              one with a lot of "tourists".</t>

            <t hangText="Tourism:  "><vspace />Variety in site-seeing
              experiences.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="criteria" title="Venue Selection Criteria">

      <t>A number of criteria are considered during the site selection process.
        The list following is not sorted in any particular order, but includes
        the committee's major considerations.</t>
      <t>The selection of a Venue always requires trade-offs. There are no
        perfect venues. For example, a site might not have a single hotel that
        can accommodate a significant number of the attendees of a typical IETF.
        That doesn't disqualify it, but it might reduce its desirability in the
        presence of an alternative that does.</t>
      <t>Many of the evaluation criteria are subjective. This might even be the
        case for criteria labeled as "Mandatory". For this reason, the IAOC and
        Meetings Committee will specifically review, and affirm to their
        satisfaction, that all "Mandatory" labeled criteria are satisfied by a
        particular Venue, as part of the process defined below in <xref
          target="steps" />.</t>

      <t>Three terms describe the places for which the IETF contracts
          services:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Venue:  "><vspace />This is an umbrella term for the
            city, meeting resources and guest room resources.</t>
          <t hangText="Facility:  "><vspace />These contain meeting rooms and
            associated resources, and possibly also contain hotel rooms.</t>
          <t hangText="IETF Hotels:  "><vspace />One or more hotels, in close
            proximity to the Facility, where the primary IETF guest room
            allocations are negotiated and IETF SSIDs are in use.</t>
        </list></t>

      <!--<texttable style="all" align="left">
          <ttcol>Criteria</ttcol> <ttcol>Required</ttcol> 
          <c></c>          <c></c> 
          <c></c>          <c></c> 
          <c></c>          <c></c> 
          <c></c>          <c></c> 
          <c></c>          <c></c> 
          </texttable> -->
<!--
      <section anchor="city" title="Venue City Criteria">
        <t>These concern basic aspects of a candidate city:</t>

        <texttable align="left" style="all">
          <ttcol>Criteria</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Required</ttcol>

          <c>Travel to the Venue is acceptable based on cost, time, and burden
            for participants traveling from multiple regions. It is anticipated
            that the burden borne will be generally shared over the course of
            multiple years.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The Venue is assessed as favorable for obtaining a host and
            sponsors. That is, the Meeting is in a location and at a price that
            it is possible and probable to find a host and sponsors. </c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>It is possible to enter into a multi-event contract with the Venue
            to optimize meeting and attendee benefits, i.e., reduce
            administrative costs and reduce direct attendee costs, will be
            considered a positive factor. Such a contract can be considered
            after at least one IETF meeting has been held at the Venue.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Desired</spanx></c>

          <c>Travel barriers to entry, e.g., visa requirements that can limit
            participation, are acceptable to the IETF community. </c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>Economic, safety, and health risks associated with this Venue are
            acceptable to the IETF community. </c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>Available travel issue assessments - - such as <eref
              target="https://travel.state.gov/content/passports/en/country.html"
             /> - - have been pointed out the IETF community. [[Editor's Note:
            This mostly concerns assessing the problems getting visa's and
            making the assessment 3 years in advance. What can we do that is
            meaningful? Also, are there better citations to include? /d]]</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>
        </texttable>

      </section>

      <section anchor="basic" title="Basic Venue Criteria">
        <t>The IETF operates as an international organisational and adjusts to
          local requirements. Facilities selected for IETF Meetings conform with
          local health, safety and accessibility laws and regulations. A useful
          discussion of related considerations in evaluating this criterion is
          at: <eref
            target="http://www.sigaccess.org/welcome-to-sigaccess/resources/accessible-conference-guide/" />
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Editor's Note:  ">In the spirit of the 'international'
              focus, we need a comprehensive document that is similar to the one
              cited, but without a national focus. The current reference is
              US-specific. /d</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In addition:</t>
        <texttable align="left" style="all">
          <ttcol>Criteria</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Required</ttcol>

          <c>The Facility is adequate in size and layout to accommodate the
            meeting and foster participant interaction.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The cost of guest rooms, meeting space, meeting food and beverage
            is affordable, within the norms of business travel.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The economics of the Venue allow the meeting to be net cash
            positive.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The Facility permits holding an IETF meeting under "One Roof". That
            is, qualified meeting space and guest rooms are available in the
            same facility.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Desired</spanx></c>

          <c>The Facility permits easy wheelchair access.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The Facility is accessible by people with disabilities.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Important</spanx></c>

        </texttable>

      </section>

      <section anchor="operations"
        title="Technical Services and Operations Criteria">

        <texttable align="left" style="all">
          <ttcol>Criteria</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Required</ttcol>

          <c>The Facility's support technologies and services - - network,
            audio-video, etc. - - are sufficient for the anticipated activities
            at the meeting, or the Venue is willing to add such infrastructure
            or these support technologies and services might be provided by a
            third party, all at no - - or at an acceptable - - cost to the
            IETF.</c>

          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The Facility directly provides, or permits and facilitates, the
            delivery of a high performance, robust, unfiltered and unmodified
            IETF Network.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The IETF Hotel(s) directly provide, or else permit and facilitate,
            the delivery of a high performance, robust, unfiltered and
            unmodified Internet service for the public areas and guest rooms;
            this service is typically included in the cost of the room.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The overflow hotels provide reasonable, reliable, unfiltered
            Internet service for the public areas and guest rooms; this service
            is included in the cost of the room.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Desired</spanx></c>
        </texttable>

      </section>

      <section anchor="lodging" title="Lodging Criteria">

        <texttable align="left" style="all">
          <ttcol>Criteria</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Required</ttcol>
          <c>The IETF Hotel(s) are within close proximity to each other and the
            Venue.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>
          <c>The guest rooms at the IETF Hotel(s) are sufficient in number to
            house 1/3 or more of projected meeting attendees.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>Overflow Hotels can be placed under contract, within convenient
            travel time of the Venue and at a variety of guest room rates.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The Venue environs include budget hotels within convenient travel
            time, cost, and effort.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The IETF Hotel(s) permit easy wheelchair access.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The IETF Hotel(s) are accessible by people with disabilities.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Important</spanx></c>

          <c>The IETF Hotel should have a social space that serves as a lounge,
            conducive to planned and accidental meetings and chatting, as well
            as working online. This is often an open bar, restaurant, or seating
            area, preferably on the ground/entrance floor, but can also be a
            meeting room, arranged to facilitate communal interaction among
            attendees.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Desired</spanx></c>

        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section anchor="food" title="Food and Beverage Criteria">
        <texttable align="left" style="all">
          <ttcol>Criteria</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Required</ttcol>

          <c>The Venue environs, which includes both onsite, as well as areas
            within a reasonable walking distance or conveniently accessible by a
            short taxi, bus, or subway ride, have convenient and inexpensive
            choices for meals that can accommodate a wide range of dietary
            requirements.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>

          <c>The Venue environs include grocery shopping that will accommodate a
            wide range of dietary requirements, within a reasonable walking
            distance, or conveniently accessible by a short taxi, bus, or subway
            ride.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Important</spanx></c>

          <c>A range of attendee's health-related and religion-related dietary
            requirements can be satisfied with robust and flexible onsite
            service or through access to an adequate grocery.</c>
          <c><spanx style="verb">Mandatory</spanx></c>
        </texttable>
      </section>
    </section>
-->
<section anchor="sec_selection_req_lists" title="Requirements">
  <t>To meet the objectives outlined above, and to provide those described in <xref target="roles" /> with adequate guidance, the following criteria are to be used to guide venue selection.</t>
  <section anchor="sec_mandatory_req" title="Mandatory Requirements for Every Meeting">
    <t>Items in this section are all mandatory.  If a requirement
    cannot be met, a location under consideration is unacceptable. We
    walk away.</t>
    <t><list style="symbols">
      <t>The Venue is assessed as favorable for obtaining a host and
      sponsors. That is, the Meeting is in a location and at a price
      that it is possible and probable to find a host and
      sponsors.</t>
      <t>The economics of the Venue allow the meeting to be net cash positive.</t>
      <t>The cost of guest rooms, meeting space, and meeting food and
      beverage are affordable and within the norms of business
      travel.</t>
      <t>Authorities within the Venue's jurisdiction do not engage in formal legal
      exclusions or differential treatment on the basis of age, gender
      or gender identity, sexuality, marital status, political views,
      racial background, nationality, countries previously visited,
      religious belief or practice, or any other category of
      irrelevant discrimination.</t>
      <t>The Venue is assessed to be safe for individuals, accounting for known health
      risks and levels of violence and crime.</t>
      <t>The Facility is adequate in size and layout to accommodate the meeting and
      foster participant interaction.</t>
      <t>The Facility is accessible by people with disabilities.</t>
      <t>The Facility's support technologies and services -- network,
      audio-video, etc. -- are sufficient for the anticipated
      activities at the meeting, or the Venue is willing to add such
      infrastructure or these support technologies and services might
      be provided by a third party, all at no -- or at an acceptable
      -- cost to the IETF.</t>
      <t>The Facility directly provides, or permits and facilitates, the delivery of a
      high performance, robust, unfiltered and unmodified IETF Network.</t>
      <t>The IETF Hotel(s) directly provide, or else permit and
      facilitate, the delivery of a high performance, robust,
      unfiltered and unmodified Internet service for the public areas
      and guest rooms; this service is typically included in the cost
      of the room.</t>
      <t>The IETF Hotel(s) are within close proximity to each other
      and the Facility.</t>
      <t>The IETF Hotel(s) are accessible by people with disabilities.</t>
      <t>The guest rooms at the IETF Hotel(s) are sufficient in number to house 1/3
      or more of projected meeting attendees.</t>
      <t>Overflow hotels can be placed under contract, within convenient travel time
      of the Facility and at a variety of guest room rates.</t>
      <t>The Venue includes budget hotels within convenient travel
      time, cost, and effort of the Facility.</t>
      <t>The Facility environs, including the site itself as well as
      areas within a reasonable walking distance or conveniently
      accessible by a short taxi, bus, or subway ride, have convenient
      and inexpensive choices for meals that can accommodate a wide
      range of dietary requirements.</t>
      <t>A range of attendee's health-related and religion-related
      dietary requirements can be satisfied with robust and flexible
      onsite service or through access to an adequate grocery.</t>
    </list></t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="sec_important_req" title="Requirements That May Be Traded Off Within a Single Venue Selection or Between Multiple Venue Selections">
    <t>Items in this section do not qualify as mandatory, but are
    still highly significant.  They may be traded against one another
    such that a Venue that meets more of these criteria is on the
    whole more preferable than another that meets less of these criteria. These requirements may also be balanced across Venue selections for multiple meetings.</t>
    <t><list style="symbols">
      <t>Informal but widely-experienced (or widely-announced)
      persistent discrimination by authorities on the basis of age,
      gender or gender identity, sexuality, marital status, political
      views, racial background, nationality, countries previously
      visited, religious belief or practice, or any other category of
      irrelevant discrimination, particularly at the point of
      immigration, should be treated as an extremely negative
      consideration.</t>
      <t>Visa requirements that can limit participation are minimized or the cost and
      difficulty associated with such requirements is spread among active participants.</t>
      <t>The cost and difficulty of travel globally is spread among active
      participants.</t>
      <t>The Venue includes grocery shopping that will accommodate a
      wide range of dietary requirements, within a reasonable walking
      distance, or conveniently accessible by a short taxi, bus, or
      subway ride of the Facility and IETF Hotels.</t>
    </list></t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="sec_desirable_req" title="Desirable Venue Attributes">
    <t>This section contains a listing of attributes that are
    desirable for a Venue.  Any or all of them might not be met for a
    Venue to be acceptable, but when choosing between different Venues
    the presence of these attributes could weigh in favour of a Venue
    that offers them.  None of these may be weighed against the criteria
    outlined in <xref target="sec_mandatory_req" /> or <xref
    target="sec_important_req" />.</t>
    <t><list style="symbols">
      <t>It is possible to enter into a multi-event contract with the
      Venue to optimize meeting and attendee benefits, i.e., reduce
      administrative costs and reduce direct attendee costs.</t>

      <t>The Facility permits holding an IETF meeting under "One
      Roof". That is, qualified meeting space and guest rooms are
      available in the same facility.</t> <t>The overflow hotels
      provide reasonable, reliable, unfiltered Internet service for
      the public areas and guest rooms; this service is included in
      the cost of the room.</t>

      <t>The IETF Hotel should have a social space that serves as a
      lounge, conducive to planned and accidental meetings and
      chatting, as well as working online. This is often an open bar,
      restaurant, or seating area, preferably on the ground/entrance
      floor, but can also be a meeting room, arranged to facilitate
      communal interaction among attendees.</t>
    </list></t>
  </section>
</section>
    <section anchor="roles" title="Venue Selection Roles">
      <t>The formal structure of IETF administrative support functions is
        documented in <xref target="RFC4071">BCP 101</xref>, <xref
          target="RFC4371" />, <xref target="RFC7691" />. The reader is expected
        to be familiar with the entities and roles defined by that document, in
        particular for the IASA, ISOC, IAOC and IAD. This section covers the
        meeting selection related roles of these and other parties that
        participate in the process. Note that roles beyond meeting selection,
        e.g., actually running and reporting on meetings, are outside the scope
        of this document.</t>

      <section title="The IETF Community">
        <t>While perhaps obvious, it is important to note that IETF meetings
          serve all those who contribute to the work of the IETF. This includes
          those who attend meetings, from newcomer to frequent attendee, to
          those who participate remotely, as well as those who do not attend but
          contribute to new RFCs. Potential new contributors are also considered
          in the process.</t>
        <t>IETF consensus, with respect to this meeting Venue selection process
          is judged via standard IETF process and not by any other means, e.g.,
          surveys. Surveys are used to gather information related to meeting
          venues, but not to measure consensus or to be reported as
          consensus.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IESG and IETF Chair">
        <t>The Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG) comprises the IETF
          Area Directors and the IETF Chair. Along with the IAB, the IESG is
          responsible for the management of the IETF, and is the standards
          approval board for the IETF, as described in <xref format="default"
            pageno="false" target="RFC2026">BCP9</xref>. This means that the
          IESG sets high level policies related to, among other things, meeting
          venues. The IETF Chair, among other things, relays these
          IESG-determined policies to the IAOC. The IETF Chair is also a member
          of the IAOC.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="The Internet Society">
        <t>With respect to IETF meetings, the Internet Society (ISOC): <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Executes all Venue contracts on behalf of the IETF at the request
              of the IAOC</t>
            <t>Solicits meeting sponsorships</t>
            <t>Collects all meeting-related revenues, including registration
              fees, sponsorships, hotel commissions, and other miscellaneous
              revenues</t>
          </list> ISOC also provides accounting services, such as invoicing and
          monthly financial statements. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="IETF Administrative Oversight Committee">
        <t>The IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) has the
          responsibility to oversee and select IETF meeting venues. It instructs
          the IAD to work with the Internet Society to write the relevant
          contracts. It approves the IETF meetings calendar.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IETF Administrative Support Activity">
        <t>The IETF Administrative Support Activity (IASA) supports the meeting
          selection process. This includes identifying, qualifying and reporting
          on potential meeting sites, as well as supporting meeting Venue
          contract negotiation. The IETF Secretariat is part of the IASA under
          the management of the IAD.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IETF Administrative Director">
        <t>The IETF Administrative Director (IAD) coordinates and supports the
          activities of the IETF Secretariat, the IAOC Meetings Committee and
          the IAOC to ensure the timely execution of the meeting process. This
          includes participating in the IAOC Meeting Subcommittee and ensuring
          its efforts are documented, leading Venue contract negotiation, and
          coordinating contract execution with ISOC. The meetings budget is
          managed by the IAD.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IAOC Meeting Committee">
        <t>The fundamental purpose of the Meetings Committee is to participate
          in the Venue selection process, and to formulate recommendations to
          the IAOC regarding meeting sites. It also tracks the meetings
          sponsorship program, recommends extraordinary meeting-related
          expenses, and recommends the IETF meetings calendar to the IAOC. The
          charter of the committee is at: <eref
            target="https://iaoc.ietf.org/committees.html#meetings" />.</t>
        <t>Membership in the Meetings Committee is at the discretion of the
          IAOC; it includes an IAOC appointed chair, the IETF Administrative
          Director (IAD), IAOC members, representatives from the Secretariat,
          and interested members of the community.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="steps" title="Venue Selection Steps">
      <t>The following is a guideline sequence for identifying and contracting a
        Venue.</t>

      <section title="Identification">
        <t>Four years out, a process identifies cities that might be candidates
          for meetings: <list style="letters">
            <t>The IAOC selects regions and dates for meetings.</t>
            <t>A list of target cities per region is provided to the
              Secretariat, with host preferences, if known.</t>
            <t>Potential venues in preferred cities are identified and receive
              preliminary investigation, including reviews of Official Advisory
              Sources, consultation with specialty travel services, frequent
              travelers and local contacts to identify possible barriers to
              holding a successful meeting in the target cities.</t>
            <t>Investigated cities and findings are provided by the Secretariat
              to the Meetings Committee for further review. Meetings Committee
              makes a recommendation to the IAOC of investigated/target cities
              to consider further as well as issues identified and the results
              of research conducted.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Consultation">
        <t>Preliminary question:<list style="letters">
            <t>The IAOC asks the community whether there are any barriers to
              holding a successful meeting in any of the target cities.
              Community responses are reviewed and concerns investigated.</t>
            <t> On a public web page, the IAOC lists all candidate cities, when
              community input was solicited, and a summarization of the review
              results. </t>
            <t> The IAOC then provides a list of vetted cities to the Meetings
              Committee to pursue as potential meeting locations.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Qualification">
        <t>Visit: <list style="letters">
            <t>Secretariat assesses "vetted" target cities to determine
              availability and conformance to criteria.</t>
            <t>Meetings Committee approves potential cities for site
              qualification visit.</t>
            <t>Site qualification visits are arranged by Secretariat and
              preliminary negotiations are undertaken with selected potential
              sites.</t>
            <t>Site qualification visit is conducted using the checklist from
                <eref
                target="https://iaoc.ietf.org/meetings-committee/venue-selection.html"
               />; the site visit team prepares a site report and discusses it
              with the Meetings Committee.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Negotiation">
        <t>2.75 - 3 years out, initiate contract negotiations: <list
            style="letters">
            <t>The Meetings Committee reviews the Venue options based on Venue
              selection criteria and recommends a Venue to the IAOC. Only
              options that meet all Mandatory labeled criteria might be
              recommended.</t>
            <t>IAOC selects a Venue for contracting as well as a back-up
              contracting Venue, if available.</t>
            <t>Secretariat negotiates with selected Venue. IAD reviews contract
              and requests IAOC and ISOC approval of contract and authority for
              Secretariat to execute contract on ISOC's behalf.</t>
            <t>Contracts are executed.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Final Check">
        <t>&tilde;3 Months prior to the Meeting, the site is checked for
          continued availability and conformance to expectations. <list
            style="letters">
            <t>Secretariat reviews current status of the contracted meeting
              location to confirm there is no change in the location status and
              to identify possible new barriers to holding a successful meeting
              in the contracted city and provides findings to the IAOC.</t>
            <t>IAOC considers the information provided and evaluates the risk -
              if significant risk is identified, the Contingency Planning Flow
              Chart (<eref
                target="https://iaoc.ietf.org/meetings-committee/venue-selection.html"
               />) is followed, if current risk is not significant, the
              situation is monitored through the meeting to ensure there is no
              significant change.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Text carried forward">
      <t>This document is being reorganized along an outline proposed by Alissa
        Cooper. In preceding sections, her comment is made explicit. That is
        intended to be removed when the reorganization is complete. Text in this
        section is left over and will potentially be moved to preceding
        sections.</t>

      <section anchor="principles-old" title="Venue Selection Process">
        <t>The process of selecting a Venue is described below and is based on
            <eref target="https://iaoc.ietf.org/venue-selection.html" />.</t>

        <section anchor="principles-logic" title="Venue Selection Principles">
          <t>heading paragraph moved to <xref target="objectives" />. <list
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Who are we?">We are computer scientists, engineers,
                network operators, academics, and other interested parties
                sharing the goal of making the Internet work better. At this
                time, the vast majority of attendees come from North America,
                Western and Central Europe, and Eastern Asia. We also have
                participants from other regions.</t>
              <t hangText="Why do we meet?">Moved to <xref format="default"
                  pageno="false" target="objectives" />.</t>
              <t hangText="Where do we meet?">moved to <xref format="default"
                  pageno="false" target="core" /></t>
              <t hangText="Inclusiveness:">Moved to <xref format="default"
                  pageno="false" target="core" />.</t>
              <t hangText="Internet Access:">Moved to <xref format="default"
                  pageno="false" target="core" />.</t>
              <t hangText="Focus:">Moved to <xref format="default"
                  pageno="false" target="core" />.</t>
              <t hangText="Economics:">Moved to <xref format="default"
                  pageno="false" target="core" />.</t>
              <t hangText="Political considerations:">moved to <xref
                  target="nonobjectives" /> and reworded per Alissa's suggested
                text.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Venue Selection Objectives">
          <t>Venues for meetings are selected to advance the objectives of the
            IETF, which are discussed in <eref
              target="https://www.ietf.org/about/mission.html" />. The IAOC's
            supporting objectives include: <list style="symbols">
              <t>Advancing standards development</t>
              <t>Facilitating participation by active contributors</t>
              <t>Sharing the travel pain; balancing travel time and expense
                across the regions from where IETF participants are based.</t>
              <t>Encouraging new contributors</t>
              <t>Generating funds to support IETF operations in support of
                standards development, including the Secretariat, IASA, and the
                RFC Editor.</t>
            </list></t>
          <t>There is an explicit intent to rotate meeting locations equally
            among several places in accordance with IETF policy. However, a
            consistent balance is sometimes difficult to achieve. The IAOC has
            an objective of setting the Regions 4 years in advance, meeting in
            Europe, North America, and Asia, with a possibility of occasionally
            meeting outside those regions. This policy, known as the 1-1-1*
            model, is set by the IESG, <eref
              target="https://iaoc.ietf.org/minutes/2010-11-10-iaoc-minutes.txt"
             />, and is further discussed in <xref format="default"
              pageno="false" target="I-D.krishnan-ietf-meeting-policy" />. The
            reason for the multi-year timeframe is maximization of
            opportunities; the smaller the time available to qualify and
            contract a conference Venue, the more stress imposed on the
            qualification process, and the greater the risk of not finding a
            suitable Venue or paying more for it.</t>
          <t>There is no formal policy regarding rotation of regions, the time
            of year for a meeting in a specific region, or whether a meeting in
            a non-targeted region replaces a visit to one of the regions during
            that year.</t>
          <t>The IETF chair drives selection of "*" locations, i.e., venues
            outside the usual regions, and requires community input. These
            selections usually arise from evidence of growing interest and
            participation in the new region. Expressions of interest from
            possible hosts also factor into the meeting site selection process,
            for any meeting.</t>
          <t>Increased participation in the IETF from those other regions,
            electronically or in person, could result in basic changes to the
            overall pattern, and we encourage those who would like for that to
            occur to encourage participation from those regions.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Venue Selection Criteria">
          <t>Heading text moved to <xref target="criteria" />.</t>
          <section anchor="venueCisty_consideration-Old"
            title="Venue City Considerations">
            <t>
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Consideration will be given to whether it makes sense to
                  enter into a multi-event contract with the Venue to optimize
                  meeting and attendee benefits, i.e., reduce administrative
                  costs and reduce direct attendee costs. [Would be nice]</t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Basic Venue Criteria">
            <t>
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>moved to "basic" <!--<xref target="basic" />--></t>
                <t>The Facility and Hotels can be put under contract. The
                  subsequent failure to put a selected Venue under contract will
                  result in a re-evaluation of the venues and selection for the
                  meeting. [Mandatory]</t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Venue Selection Phases" />

        <section title="Experience Notes">
          <t>
            <list style="letters">
              <t>The foregoing process works with reasonable certainty in North
                America and Europe.</t>
              <t>Experience to date for Asia and Latin America is that contracts
                take longer and often will not be executed more than two years
                in advance of the meeting. While the IETF will have the first
                option for the dates, for reasons not completely understood
                contracts won't be executed.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Transparency">
        <t>BCP 101 requires transparency in IASA process and contracts, and
          thereby of the meetings committee. BCP 101 also states that the IAOC
          approves what information is to remain confidential. Therefore any
          information produced by the meetings committee or related to meetings
          that individuals believe is confidential, e.g., venue contracts, must
          be confirmed to be confidential by the IAOC.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo asks the IANA for no new parameters.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This note proposes no protocols, and therefore no new protocol
        insecurities.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>This note reveals no personally identifying information apart from its
        authorship.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document was originally assembled and edited by Fred Baker.
        Additional commentary came from Jari Arkko, Scott Bradner, and Alissa
        Cooper. It was discussed on mtgvenue@ietf.org.</t>
    </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!--references split to informative and normative -->
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2026"
        target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2026">

        <front>
          <title>The Internet Standards Process -- Revision 3</title>
          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="1996" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This memo documents the process used by the Internet community
              for the standardization of protocols and procedures. It defines
              the stages in the standardization process, the requirements for
              moving a document between stages and the types of documents used
              during this process. This document specifies an Internet Best
              Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests
              discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="9" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2026" />
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2026" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4071"
        target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4071">
        <front>
          <title>Structure of the IETF Administrative Support Activity
            (IASA)</title>
          <author fullname="R. Austein" initials="R." role="editor"
            surname="Austein">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author fullname="B. Wijnen" initials="B." role="editor"
            surname="Wijnen">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2005" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the structure of the IETF Administrative
              Support Activity (IASA) as an activity housed within the Internet
              Society (ISOC). It defines the roles and responsibilities of the
              IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC), the IETF
              Administrative Director (IAD), and ISOC in the fiscal and
              administrative support of the IETF standards process. It also
              defines the membership and selection rules for the IAOC. This
              document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the
              Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for
              improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4071" />
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC4071" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4371"
        target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4371">
        <front>
          <title>BCP 101 Update for IPR Trust</title>
          <author fullname="B. Carpenter" initials="B." role="editor"
            surname="Carpenter">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author fullname="L. Lynch" initials="L." role="editor"
            surname="Lynch">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2006" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document updates BCP 101 to take account of the new IETF
              Intellectual Property Trust. This document specifies an Internet
              Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests
              discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4371" />
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC4371" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7691"
        target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7691">
        <front>
          <title>Updating the Term Dates of IETF Administrative Oversight
            Committee (IAOC) Members</title>
          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." role="editor"
            surname="Bradner">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2015" />
          <abstract>
            <t>BCP 101 defines the start and end dates for the terms of IETF
              Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) members; these terms
              have proven to be impractical. This memo updates BCP 101 to direct
              the IAOC to establish more practical start and end dates for terms
              of IAOC members.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="101" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7691" />
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7691" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.krishnan-ietf-meeting-policy">
        <front>
          <title>High level guidance for the meeting policy of the IETF</title>
          <author fullname="Suresh Krishnan" initials="S" surname="Krishnan">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date day="8" month="July" year="2016" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes a proposed meeting policy for the IETF
              and the various stakeholders for realizing such a policy.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
          value="draft-krishnan-ietf-meeting-policy-01" />
        <format
          target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-krishnan-ietf-meeting-policy-01.txt"
          type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MeetingNet">
        <front>
          <title>IETF Meeting Network Requirements</title>
          <author fullname="Karen O'Donoghue" initials="K." surname="O'Donoghue" />
          <author fullname="Jim Martin" initials="J." surname="Martin" />
          <author fullname="Chris Elliott" initials="C." surname="Elliott" />
          <author fullname="Joel Jaeggli" initials="J." surname="Jaeggli" />
          <date />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="WEB"
          value="https://iaoc.ietf.org/ietf-network-requirements.html" />
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor="RFC3935">

        <front>
          <title>A Mission Statement for the IETF</title>
          <author fullname="H. Alvestrand" initials="H." surname="Alvestrand">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2004" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This memo gives a mission statement for the IETF, tries to define
              the terms used in the statement sufficiently to make the mission
              statement understandable and useful, argues why the IETF needs a
              mission statement, and tries to capture some of the debate that
              led to this point. This document specifies an Internet Best
              Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests
              discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="95" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3935" />
        <format octets="16639"
          target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3935.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.barnes-healthy-food">
        <front>
          <title>Healthy Food and Special Dietary Requirements for IETF
            meetings</title>
          <author fullname="Mary Barnes" initials="M" surname="Barnes">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date day="16" month="July" year="2013" />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the basic requirements for food for folks
              that attend IETF meetings require special diets, as well as those
              that prefer to eat healthy. While, the variety of special diets is
              quite broad, the most general categories are described. There can
              be controversy as to what constitutes healthy eating, but there
              are some common, generally available foods that comprise the basis
              for healthy eating and special diets. This document provides some
              recommendations to meeting planners, as well as participants, in
              handling these requirements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-barnes-healthy-food-07" />
        <format
          target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-barnes-healthy-food-07.txt"
          type="TXT" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="I-D.sullivan-mtgvenue-decisions">
        <front>
          <title>Prioritized Objectives for Making Decisions in Selecting a Meeting Venue</title>
          <author fullname="Andrew Sullivan" initials="A" surname="Sullivan">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author fullname="Alissa Cooper" initials="A" surname="Cooper">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date day="8" month="July" year="2016" />
          <abstract>
            <t>Selecting a site for an IETF meeting necessarily involves balancing
   various factors about the site and the goals of the IETF meeting.
   Those who are faced with choosing a site need guidance on how to
   prioritize objectives in making such decisions, since no algorithm is
   possible.  This memo provides a set of such objectives in order of
   importance.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-sullivan-mtgvenue-decisions-00" />
        <format
          target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-sullivan-mtgvenue-decisions-00.txt"
          type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>


    <section anchor="log" title="Change Log">
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="2016-01-12:">Initial version</t>
          <t hangText="2016-01-21:">Update to reflect
            https://iaoc.ietf.org/documents/VenueSelectionCriteriaJan2016.pdf
            and
            https://iaoc.ietf.org/documents/VenueSelectionProcess11Jan16.pdf,
            accessed from
            https://iaoc.ietf.org/private/privatemeetings.html.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-02-23:">Reorganize and capture IAOC Meetings
            Committee discussions.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-03-03:">Final from Design Team.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-03-17:">First update incorporating mtgvenue@ietf.org
            comments</t>
          <t hangText="2016-05-20">Updated in accordance with editing by Laura
            Nugent, Dave Crocker, Lou Berger, Fred Baker, and others.</t>
          <t hangText="posting as working group draft">August 2, 2016</t>
          <t hangText="Reorganized per Alissa Cooper outline">Work in progress.
            In addition, contributors were re-organized to be authors.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-10-28">Editor changeover. Further alignment with
            guidance by Alissa Cooper, Andrew Sullivan and the mtgvenue working
            group. Many various changes.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-11-16">Extensive editorial, format and polishing
            pass. A few substance changes, including food section.</t>
          <t hangText="2016-11-30">Additions based on working group meeting and
            off-list discussions; more editorial and format hacking.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
